Tom Hiatt

Metro Manila, National Capital Region, Philippines



hiattt@who.int



linkedin.com/in/tom-hiatt-8180b037

Summary

Experienced public health professional interested in eHealth, mHealth, infectious diseases, health emergencies, data visualization, country development, effective social interventions, social business/enterprise, and any other solutions that supplement limited resources to improve the lives of people everywhere.

Experience



Public Health Specialist, Tuberculosis & Rabies

World Health Organization

Jun 2019 - Present (2 years +)

Supported massive scale-up of tuberculosis (TB) screening, testing, treatment and prevention under the Race to End TB campaign resulting in a 15% year-on-year increase in cases found.

Developed and designed four mobile apps for the End TB App Suite (http://ntp.doh.gov.ph/apps) and the COVID-19 surveillance system, COVIDKAYA.

Supported the National Rabies Prevention and Control Program with joint annual reports from the human and animal sectors, improved data flows, technical advisories, national vaccination campaigns, a rapid response toolkit, and health promotion.

Created the contact tracing handbook to support the national COVID-19 response.



Monitoring And Evaluation Specialist, Health Emergencies

World Health Organization

Jan 2017 - Jun 2019 (2 years 6 months)

Created an internal implementation monitoring systems to ensure effective results-based activities were conducted according to the WHO Planning, Budgeting and Monitoring Framework.

Planned and conducted a training workshop on After Action Reviews and Simulation Exercises.

Created an M&E database to collect and store all M&E activities under the IHR Monitoring and Evaluation Framework as well as National Action Plans and Pandemic Preparedness Plans.



Epidemiologist, Tuberculosis and Leprosy

World Health Organization

Jan 2012 - Dec 2016 (5 years)

Analysed and created tables and figures for eight annual global TB control reports (2007 to 2014 datasets).

Conducted in-depth programme reviews in Viet Nam, Mongolia, Papua New Guinea and the Philippines.

Developed mobile apps for TB and leprosy including programme directory and leprosy disability assessment tool with high user acceptance.



Health Data Analyst, Tuberculosis

World Health Organization

Jan 2007 - Jan 2012 (5 years 1 month)

Created four Global TB control reports as part of core writing team (www.who.int/tb/publications/ global report). Led data management and analysis for "Improving TB estimates" workshops in all 6 WHO regions.

Taught 10 plus trainings for the WHO Health Data Forum including trainings on R and STATA. Conceptualized re-design of order management system for Global Drug Facility. Designed TB technical assistance coordination web tool.

Education

London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, U. of London

MSc, Epidemiology 2010 - 2013



Brigham Young University

BA, Visual art, Media art 2001 - 2005

Skills

R • Stata • Data Collection • Reports • Data Processing • Data Visualization • Epidemiology • Analysis • Global Health • Data Management